Amongst themselves for a 30 minutes for around
about 30 minutes and then we will follow
up with a 30 minutes question and answer session
and at this point you'll have an opportunity to
put forward your questions yourself to the panel.
So I'll be calling the names, and then you'll
get an opportunity to to ask your questions.
I think some of you may have submitted questions
before so the panel will try we've only got a
short slot which also I'll keep quiet in a minute
but then the panel will try and answer all your
questions to the best they can. So, we'll try
and fit quite a lot in. So without further ado,
I will call on the first speaker Dr. Arday, may I
ask you to lead on your five minutes provocation?
Thank you that's great. Thank you so much everyone
good morning. I hope you're all keeping well.
Good morning Councillor Williams and to the
rest of the panel. It's really good to see
everyone and thanks for everyone's taking
the time to be here on a Thursday morning.
I guess we're living in a really turbulent time
right now in terms of how we define Britishness
and belonging. The hostile environment
is thriving at the expense of Black
and ethnic minority people so it's really
interesting to think about this idea of history
and in particular British history.
And what comprises that history
and the kind of historical amnesia that
ensues when we're talking about history,
generally speaking, which completely omits the
contribution of Black and ethnic minorities to
Empire, British legacy, British infrastructure,
the economy - all of those things
over many centuries. So, I guess the
thing I want to talk about is really
what that looks like in our educational spaces.
And I suppose the thing that becomes really
pertinent when considering these things, is
that sense of belonging within the classroom.
And education as itself is a microcosm of society.
So it's this microcosm of society yet we have this
cannon of education that isn't actually reflective
of a multicultural, multi-ethnic, multi-diverse
society. So when individuals are going into that
classroom space, there is a disconnect and an
absence in terms of belonging because you're not
actually seeing aspects of your own diaspora,
indigenous populous, lived experience reflected
in the curriculum that you're engaging with. And
I think one of the things that becomes really
important is the impact upon attainment. Now
Black students, ethnic minority students,
against what is inherently an institutionally
racist and disadvantaging education system have
flourished. Have flourished over the last 50 to
60 years as it's noted in the Robbins Report
(1963), the Scarman Report (1981) and other
reports that have resurfaced since then probably
most latterly the MacPherson Report in 1999. But
one of the recommendations under the first report
in 1999 in terms of becoming racially literate and
racially cognizant was this understanding around
embedding Black history within our national
curriculum as a British history not as a separate
history, devolved of a white dominant Eurocentric
narrative. So, I think that becomes really,
really important because what we are seeing is
an education system that is systematically
failing, particularly young Black boys.
And I think it's also important to acknowledge
that it's to everyone's benefit to have this
type of knowledge, because it facilitates
the society we live in. The whole purpose
of education, in many ways, is to prepare people
to take their place within society. And education
is failing all of its inhabitants by not providing
them with the tools, the information, they need to
circumnavigate or to navigate, a multicultural and
diverse society. From an attainment point of view,
what we are seeing is that absence of cognition
and relation to looking at a curriculum that
actually "I'm seeing people that look like me"
that moves beyond entertainment or music. That has
always been funneled into one area. I think it's
really important we think about the contributions
of Black and ethnic minority people, particularly
over the last 100 years to the British context.
In terms of attainment, what we are seeing are
deficits that really revealed themselves, not only
in secondary education but all the way through to
higher education. And what we're seeing is that
while we continue to have ethnic minority students
going to university in record numbers, just under
half the university population in the UK are
Black and ethnic minorities, the outcomes still
continue to be pretty poor in terms of the actual
attainment gap which for the higher education
remains at 23 per cent. There have been
institutions that have managed to reduce that
to varying degrees, but fundamentally what we're
still struggling with is that deficit in terms of
how all people access education, and how we
omit particular types of education and the
centrality of a dominant, white, euro-centric
knowledge cannon, which completely omits
and marginalizes different types of knowledge.
And in doing that, and having those kind of
gatekeepers, and those kind of custodians, what
we're actually doing is further placing Black
and ethnic minority people on the periphery of
educational spaces and having better educational
outcomes. So, I think the most important thing
is, for us as a collective and moving forward, to
think about how we change those spaces to ensure
better outcomes for young Black people and ethnic
minorities. I think the pipeline between education
and prison is one that probably needs to be
forensically more examined. Because the high
exclusion rate of young black boys for example,
between the ages of 13 and 16, do lead them on
that pathway to that. We need to think about how
the education system is actually facilitating
that because, in terms of the 2011 census,
14 per cent of the population are Black and ethnic
minorities 3 per cent are Black, but you still
have a huge percentage of that 3 per cent that
make up a lot of the prison population in the
UK. So it's thinking about how we disrupt those
patterns and thinking about aspects of curriculum
and attainment. How we establish belonging
pedagogically in the classroom become really
essential in terms of doing that. I think that's
me so thank you so much and I'm really looking
forward to hearing what everyone else has to say.
So thank you for your time, I'm really grateful
Hi everyone. I think I'm next am I?
Martha you're definitely next. Please go ahead.
Okay you just appeared, sorry about that. Without
an introduction. Hi everybody. This is Martha
Holder, one of our primary Head Teachers.
Please go ahead and introduce yourself properly.
Thank you. Okay, thank you. Thank you for that.
I mean it's a real privilege to be on this
panel and to be asked to be here today.
I think that in terms of what's happening,
I'd like to just reiterate and just share
my experiences of COVID and of Black Lives Matter.
I was deeply, deeply shocked by what happened in
terms of, I wouldn't say a murder, I would say
an execution, that took place in front of us.
And many millions of us were able to see that. And
I think in terms of that, it's really important
that the work that we're doing, does continue.
And I know that that's been reiterated by most
of the panel with regards to that. I'd like
to say, that I think that Greenwich is doing
a great job in acknowledging what took place.
They had the installation back in, I think it was
June, down by Tesco's, which had the big poster on
the floor for Black Lives Matter. And as a school,
we really do try to tackle those difficult
conversations with our children. So during
COVID-19, we set some homework for the children,
it was by Google because obviously not all
children are in school, where children really got
to understand the difference between Black Lives
Matter, and All Lives Matter. And it's about us
really being brave and taking a risk, and actually
having those conversations and giving the children
the platform to share their experiences and
to really make informed decisions, not just
stereotypes or reiterate what they've heard.
I think that in terms of education, I feel
really optimistic about education. I think that
there's so many opportunities for us to really
change how we can change how things happen in the
past, and how we can shape the future as a school.
We don't do Black History Month per se, because
we think it's part of the whole curriculum.
So we have diversity throughout the year.
This year, this term, we're doing diversity
looking at Diversity, Power and Politics,
and it's throughout the school from Year 1
reading the story Amazing Grace, to Year 6,
looking at really challenging texts. So,
I think that there is a lot of work that
we can do, and a lot of things that we
can do, to really empower our children.
But we do know that the statistics we do know,
fundamentally that something happens in primary
school and something happens when the children get
to secondary school. And it's a conversation that
has been going on for decades. I would say
when I was at university, the Swan Report
spoke about the disparity between young
Black boys and the education system. And
I think it's really important that we
have people from diverse backgrounds,
that children see themselves as educators.
And I'd like to add on with what Adel said
that it goes beyond a superstar, it goes beyond
somebody singing, it goes beyond somebody being
a sports person. But we look at those different
industries that Black people are marginalized in,
and actually challenge that and allow children
to have experience of people from different
backgrounds doing different roles. We were really
fortunate in terms of the children in our school,
that we were able to work with a lady called Grace
who has put together a great maths game 'Race to
Infinity'. Children need to experience, know that
their experiences are acknowledged and the only
way that really does happen, really fundamentally,
is if they can relate to people, if people can
really recognize their experiences. So in terms
of secondary school children, and the experience
of our Black children in secondary school, it's
really important that we speak to them so that
it's not just a panel making decisions but
their voice is heard. I think we have to have
aspirations for all of our children, and be really
ambitious and fight for what they they deserve.
Children at Mulgrave deserve the best education.
I know that Greenwich has high expectations of its
children. The Director [of Children's Services],
Florence Kroll, has set up a Black Lives Matter
working party, which says a lot. We will
be tackling really difficult issues, and
challenging issues, and it will be uncomfortable.
I think we have to be able to get uncomfortable
to move forward. But I would like to hope that we
are all really ambitious for the children. And I
know that I can speak for Mulgrave School, that
we only expect the best for our children. We want
to give them the best. And I can say that about
other schools in Greenwich as well. So, there
is a lot of work to do. It is a challenge. But I
think that there is the possibility to really make
that fundamental change, and give children a love
of education, and for them to realize that it can
really take them to real far, far gone places.
The world's getting smaller now with COVID-19,
we can't travel as much, but I still want
children to be ambitious about travelling
and going to other places and being in careers
that they may not have considered before.
Thank you very much Ms. Holder. Sorry about
that. I didn't introduce you properly.
Thank you. Thank you Dr. Arday for sharing
your five minutes' thoughts at this time.
I'm going to invite Dr. Jivraj to speak to us.
Is Dr. Jivraj here? I can't see her online.
Hi, yes. I was just waiting to be unmuted.
Okay I think this works now. Can everyone
hear me? Someone give me a thumbs up. Yeah, okay.
Great, thank you so much for inviting me to speak
to Greenwich today. I'm from the University of
Kent. I'm based in the Law School there and we
have a campus in Chatham Maritime along with the
University of Kent, so there are connections there
which are particularly personal to me because
I've spent a long time teaching on that campus
and getting to know a lot of students who
come there from the Greenwich vicinity.
Great, so as I said I'm in the Law School
and I teach public law which is one of the,
it's the flagship module that all our
incoming students do in their first year.
It's a compulsory module. We have a cohort
between 450 to 700 depending on the year.
So, it's a real privilege, I think, to be able to
have access to these amazing young minds who are
eager to learn and have their thinking really
challenged in this new university context.
And as part of that module, I introduce them into
various comparative and international ideas of
constitutional law. How democracy works. How the
history of democracy, but not just in relation to
what we're used to hearing about, so for example
the French and the American revolutions, and how
the Enlightenment period gave rise to democracy as
we understand it now in the modern era, but also
in relation to post-apartheid South Africa,
in relation to indigenous moves towards
constitutionality in South America, the slave
rebellions in Haiti which gave rise to the first
constitution, modern constitution, as we know it.
And, so they get this kind of barrage from me,
of all this information that they're
not expecting, because it's so different
from what they're used to in terms of a very
white curriculum. And, so by the time they
reach my Third Year module, which is an optional
module, I get students who are really keen to put,
get their teeth into, this material in much more
detail. And that module is Race, Religion and Law.
And more recently, we've been taking a very
intersectional approach to it, so thinking about
the intersections between race, religion, gender
and sexuality, as well. And, what I hear by the
time the third year students reach me, is "Wow,
why did we not do more of this in first year?",
"Why don't I know about this history about how
the law was constituted and how it's perpetuated
so much violence against black people and people
of colour across the world?". And not only that,
so it's not just you know the
Zong case which talks about
how slave traders were compensated for
supposed loss of cargo, basically murdering
of slaves on board these slave ships,
but also in relation to knowledge that
is out there coming from amazing lawyers
in Africa, Asia. And that they don't know
about this knowledge that is produced and I heard
Claire Alexander recently who I know works with
Jason [Dr. Arday], and she was saying that we have
this perception that information isn't out there,
we need to go digging for Black history, or Black
scholars of this body of scholarship. That we're
so fixated, and the fact that the white canon
is all there is, and that's simply not true.
And so bringing this other knowledge to students
at all levels, not just in higher education,
but at all levels, which wonderful organizations
like The Black Curriculum, Kids of Color and other
initiatives are now doing and calling upon the
government I think is really, really essential.
So as a lawyer, I'm just going to remind you,
because I actually have to do this with my own
colleagues in in higher education
in Law Schools, and remind them
that we are under a legal duty under the Equality
Act, under the Public Sector Equality Duty,
to provide education in a non-discriminatory
way. Certainly in Higher Education, we've had
the recent Equality and Human Rights Commission
inquiry into racial harassment, and this is really
the latest report on a plethora, a barrage,
of reports. So, we know there's a problem.
We also know about attainment gaps both in
primary and secondary education, but also
in higher education. And the terminology that's
used is, attainment gaps. Actually, the first time
I heard that term used in a departmental meeting,
I was absolutely outraged and I was thinking,
"What what are you talking about?". I prefer
to use the language of attack, not 'attainment
disparities' but 'awarding disparities', because
the problem as many have have written about, Jason
[Dr. Arday], Robbie Shilliam and many others, is
that it's contingent on this idea of students as
somehow lacking. Somehow having a cultural, and
educational, and other forms of deficit. And,
actually in that discourse, there is no mention
of institutional racism, of systemic racism,
and really that's what is part of what I'm doing,
is trying to shift some of the focus on to that,
and I'll come on to that in a minute.
I was awarded some funding by the Socio-Legal
Studies Association, to put together the resource
that I recently launched. It's available. It's
an anti-racist, legal pedagogy resource.
It's relevant though beyond just the law,
and it's available for free to download.
I think the link is on the next slide.
As part of that, l interviewed law teachers
who I knew were already doing amazing critical
scholarship and teaching. And one
of the interviewees said to me,
"the attainment gap as it's known is
definitely a product of what we teach".
What we can do in the university,
and I'd say education more broadly,
is to reflect on what we're teaching, how
we're teaching, and also, how we're assessing.
And when I saw this photo from
one of the BLM protests it really,
it talks to that point, that Martha mentioned
about discomfort, which I'm going to come back to.
Actually, yes, people find it scary, but we
need to remind ourselves that as educators,
it's a privilege to educate yourself about racism,
instead of actually having to experience it,
so let's contemplate and
reflect on that for a moment.
Here are some of my wonderful students. So
the project 'Decolonizing the Curriculum'
is unique in the sense that most decolonizing the
curriculum projects are either student movements,
or institutional initiatives
that come under the guise of
equality, diversity and inclusion, or student
success, as they're more recently calling it.
This project, which I
initiated, was with my students.
This project I initiated with the students that I
teach, because as this discourse around attainment
gaps was coming out, and becoming bigger, I was
getting really angry. I was discussing it with
students in class, because it didn't reflect
my experience of the students that I teach.
So, I put together a funding bid for
some Innovation in Teaching funds,
and we were awarded it. Essentially, the students
conducted their own research. So what was really
interesting and innovative about this project,
is that I and my colleagues trained the students
to become researchers. So they went through
a whole process, from ethics approval, to
literature reviews, to writing skills, research
skills, focus group training skills, and then they
led these focus groups with the other students
and and they led them in what we called "Colonial
Cafe" style environments, and they led. They
chose the theme, so they had specific groups for
Black men, Muslim women, around mental health,
around well-being, international students,
so they really focused in on some of the issues
that they felt were most pressing for them.
They created this manifesto and they
launched it at a conference in March 2019.
The link on the bottom of the slide there you can
see the manifesto footage from the conference,
and the other resources that they've
created - a reading list and so on.
They went on to actually train
staff, so their expertise and their
knowledge went into their training staff, both
within our university and also externally.
And, actually one of the students,
Lisa, you can see they're presenting
the manifesto to the Speaker of the
House of Commons, she has recorded
a lovely video about the project, which you can
see on that page and recounts it in more detail.
I would encourage you to go and see for yourself.
Someone who started off as a undergraduate student
went through quite a difficult time, has been
part of this process, and is now completing her
Master's in Research so you know as Jason
[Dr. Arday] said, there's that pipeline.
The other wonderful thing about the project was
that it really continued, or helped to continue,
the pipeline and the interaction between
the students themselves, creating a sense of
belonging and taking up space. There's more I can
say about how we did how we went about creating
what we call 'principal spaces' rather than 'safe
spaces', because we can't guarantee safe spaces so
you know working through principles,
and all the information is on the web.
Coming back to this idea of discomfort, as
we were engaging in this project, there was
everything that we were doing with the
students to get the word out there,
but also a lot of Law School teachers were
coming to me and saying, "Listen, you know
what you're doing! This looks great. How
can I do something? How can I get started?"
There's a real kind of sense of be feeling
stuck, and not knowing how to get started,
and that's why I put together this resource
which has a set of prompts, readings, cases,
for law school teachers, for teachers to think
about in getting started in their foundational
subjects, where they often think "oh, we don't
have enough time. I'm already overloaded".
It's meant to be a getting started process
for those who really have the motivation,
but don't know how, or where to get started.
I think a key thing that comes out of the
policy that we really need to remember, and in
particular, this report that came out in 2019,
and in the bottom corner there in the
black hoodie you'll see one of my students.
In the report they make five recommendations. And
one of the recommendations is that universities
need to have conversations about race.
And this includes whiteness, because race
is not just about people of colour, and someone
else's issue, actually, it's white people's issue.
Whiteness and systemic racism, and leadership,
within these institutions. It is an issue of
whiteness, and we really need to look at that.
So, a big chunk of the resource is also about
how to get started in looking at the issues where
you are. What are the blockages? People obviously
think they know what racism is and recently
there's the term racial microaggression,
and you've got the work of people like Dr.
Nicola Rollock, and the brilliant work by Dr.
Remi Joseph-Salisbury, on this issue of racism,
and we really need to acknowledge how we're all
complicit in these behaviors in various ways.
So this defensiveness and discomfort about
actually being willing to acknowledge how we
are complicit, that really is the first hurdle.
Before we can get to thinking about how we can
change our curriculum and all the rest of it,
I really think that we need to reflect on
where where we are at, and what we're engaging.
Students are telling us this all the time, "I'm
not just uncomfortable with what I'm being taught,
I'm uncomfortable in the classroom. How
I'm being treated, how I'm being profiled".
This is a wonderful kind of diagram that the
students, and artists, and other experts, came
together to put together, as a kind of process -
a stepping stone process - that is continual. So,
it's not a journey you begin and then you end. No,
it's continual. We're all always on this process.
There's much more on stepping stones, that you
can see on the web page so please do have a look.
I'm sure I've gone over time so I just want to
finish with this event, which is happening this
afternoon. It's to celebrate the launch of
the book that came out of the 'Decolonizing
the Curriculum' project. So, we worked with
the students who were part of the project,
to co-author this book and they are so excited
to be co-authors to have a publication.
If you have time to tune in to the
launch, you'll see them talking about
their experiences. What they've achieved,
but also what still needs to be done.
So, all I can say to end is that it
is an absolute privilege to work with
our students, and we owe it to them to give them
the opportunity to realize this this amazing
potential that they have. And as they say to me,
"Suhraiya, I need to self-actualize." Thank you.
Thank you very much, Dr. Jivraj, a lot to take in.
There are a lot of points that we could follow up
on, so really interesting piece of work.
I just want to recognize that you've
acknowledged in your work, that
the deficit between the attainment
has a lot to do with the award system, and that
is something that we all need to pay attention to.
Without any further ado, I just
want to finally bring to you, Ms.
Ukoumunne. If you could introduce yourself.
You've got five minutes. Sorry if it's cut short,
the previous speaker took a minute or two of your
time. I do apologize if I'll need to stop you.
No, that's absolutely fine. It's fine because
everybody has actually covered so much of what
I wanted to say which is perfect. I also want
to thank you for pronouncing my name properly.
There was a pause of a few seconds, and I thought
let's see what's going to happen. It was amazing,
well done. Thank you, and yes, everyone's covered
a lot of the points that I wanted to raise.
I think I will just start by saying my
background actually is in African literature
and drama. I'm Nigerian - it was really funny
this morning when Adel said congratulations
to all the Nigerians out there on Nigerian
Independence Day, I had completely forgotten.
I think that this is a reminder of the ways in
which we, our cultural memory, our historical
memory, about things that are important to us,
can sometimes slip by and can be hidden. And the
reason I start there, is that a lot of my work,
because I started teaching in African literature,
and I currently teach Critical Race Theory,
a lot of my work focuses on the philosophical
and epistemological questions related to
literature, and history and black philosophy.
The reason it's important for me,
is that as somebody said earlier,
we as non-white people, are in an arc of history,
particularly I'm going to focus on African people
and people from the African diaspora, it's not
because I don't think other people's histories are
important or significant, I think they are deeply,
but I think one of the dangers that we have
when we are ensconced within Eurocentric systems,
is that our histories can become muddled and
thrown together. The tag BAME for me is not always
useful, because it can sometimes hide a plethora
of inequalities and injustices, particularly when
we think about Black women's experiences. So, we
do talk a lot about Black boys' experiences, but
we don't talk about how do Black girls experience
the education system. How do they overcome
problems of gender and racial disadvantage?
We don't talk about how they experience
violence, both epistemological and
physical violence. Because they are Black andwomen, it's really important for me as somebody
who's interested in gender, to say maybe when westarted talking about decolonizing the curriculum,
we must also start foregrounding
the experiences of Black women.
As I said, my kind of philosophical approach to
this is to say we are part of, we participate in
an arc of history, our danger is that we tend to
treat the African or African Caribbean experience
as if it began in 1948. Every time I read anarticle it says the Windrush docked in 1948 and
I think, "Look, Black history is older than 1948!".
So, I think that we need to start thinking out of
ourselves as having an ancient historical
experience. We need to start thinking of
this part of our experience, unpleasant as it is
at times, but it also has its joys. Let's face it,
it's not all misery. We need to start thinking
about that as part of a long process. It's part of
a trajectory, and you know, my favourite author at
the moment, Ayi Kwei Armah, talks about the fact that
we need to look back, we need to look back to
consider the ways that what we have experienced,
brings value to us. We need to start thinking
about how the value that is brought to us through
our experience can be taken into the future, so
we need to think not in the teleological ways
that Eurocentric history functions. We shouldn't
be thinking about past, present, future. We should
be thinking about the ways in which they
are amalgamated. The ways in which the past
informs the present, and that in turn informs the
future. For me, that's quite critical, because I,
like other speakers, want to start thinking about
the ways in which we are all creating history
all of the time. History is not the preserve of
very rich or powerful people. Ordinary people,
Black women who are fighting every day to prevent
their Black boys from being excluded from schools
are actually creating history. They may
not see themselves as historical beings,
because they don't write their histories. So,
when I teach critical race theory to my students,
I emphasize the importance of
writing diaries, keeping notes,
writing your histories. In a hundred
years' time, in 200 years' time, I would be
very saddened if the history that we focus
on, is the history of social services records,
or criminal justice records. We have a history,
we participate in and are producing this society,
but it is our responsibility to make
sure that we keep records and narrate
our histories and we leave that for the benefit of
future generations. So, as this was a provocation,
a provocation piece, I don't know what
that means, but I think I'll give it a go,
I thought where I'm at. Where my mind is focusing
at the moment, as an intellectual, as a theorist
is, I am wondering whether it is possible, it is
possible for us to decolonize the institution?
James Baldwin says something very important.
He says, when you are attempting to reform the
institutions, whatever institutions they are,
are you attempting to join a burning house?
Now, I don't want to join a burning house. I
am wondering whether we need to start thinking,
is it time in the 21st century, for us to start
thinking about building our own institutions. One
of the problems that you have when you participate
in the reform of other people's institutions is,
firstly, you don't have control over the
time-scale of change. This may take 10, 20,
might take a hundred, 200 years. Who can say?
So, you don't have control over the time-scale.
The second thing that I would say is, that
you don't have control over the agenda.
And I think that our agenda might be not
that we just want to focus on Black boys,
entertainment. That's important, but we might
want an agenda that focuses on our humanity.
Can we create a world in which violence
no longer exists? Can we create a world in
which people are not oppressed because of their
economic circumstances? Can we create a world
in which the actual physical world that wepossess, that we are constantly abusing through
the exploitation of resources, can we create
a world for future generations in which these
problems no longer exist? So, I think, when I
say can we move away from the idea of reform,
my favorite author, Harold Cruse,
asks, "Do we need to focus on rebellion
or should we focus on revolution?"
And the question is one of reform.
And when I say revolution, I say, rethinking the
way that we think about the world. Changing our
consciousness. Shifting our consciousness to ask
for more. To request more, and to bring all of
our experiences to the human table, as it were,
to change the way in which history progresses.
That's all I have to say guys.
Thank you so much for your time.